"The Recommended Daily
Added Sugar Intake"
Dating back to the original Dietary Goals
for the United States in 1977—
the so-called McGovern Report—
leading nutrition scientists
were not only calling for a
reduction in meat, and other sources
of saturated fat and cholesterol,
like dairy and eggs, but also sugar.
The goal was to reduce
America’s sugar intake down
to no more than 10% of the daily diet.
“The final conclusions would hang sugar,”
reported the President
of the Sugar Association.
“The McGovern Report has
to be neutralized….”
Don’t worry, though, we have
the National Cattlemen’s Association
on our side and, like Big Sugar,
they appealed to the
Senate Select Committee
to withdraw the report.
“The Sugar Industry Empire”
striking back appeared to work.
When the official dietary
guidelines were released in 1980,
and then again in ‘85,
no specific limit like 10%,
just the vague “avoid too much
sugar,” whatever that means.
By ‘95 it got even vaguer:
“Choose a diet moderate in sugars.”
In 2000, they were at least back to
“limit,” but even that was too strong.
Under pressure from sugar
lobbyists, they went back to
“moderate your intake of sugars,”
before the 2005 guideline committee
dropped the s-word completely,
encouraging Americans to
“Choose carbohydrates
wisely,” whatever that means.
If only there were some kind
of dietary guidelines committee
that could give us guidance...
The Sugar Association expressed
optimism about that 2005 Committee.
The Sugar Association Incorporated
is “committed to the protection
and promotion of
[table sugar] consumption,”
and they will not allow for
the “disparagement of sugar.”
And, they’re not kidding.
In 2003, the World Health
Organization released a report
“Diet, nutrition and the
prevention of chronic diseases”
which, for the first time since
the McGovern Report called for
a reduction in sugar intake to under 10%.
The Sugar Association responded by
threatening to get the U.S.
to withdraw all funding from the WHO.
Here it is, in black and white.
The Sugar Association threatening to
pressure Congress to withdraw funding
from the World Health
Organization - polio vaccinations,
AIDS medications be damned, you
just don’t mess with the candy man.
The threat was described
as tantamount to blackmail
and worse than any pressure they
had experienced from Big Tobacco.
But now, 15 years later, and 40
years after the first proposed
McGovern Report, the current 2015
to 2020 Dietary Guidelines
lay out as a key recommendation
the 10% limit,
currently exceeded by every
age bracket in the United States
starting at age one, with adolescents
averaging 87 grams of sugar a day,
meaning the average teen is effectively
eating 29 sugar packets a day.
The Sugar Association describes
the 10% limit as “extremely low,”
I mean only like up to
a dozen spoonfuls a day.
But, of course, there’s no dietary
requirement for added sugar at all,
and every single calorie we get from
added sugar is a wasted opportunity
to get calories from sources
that actually provide nutrition
To the American Heart Association’s
credit, they went further
trying to push added sugar intake
down to about 6% of calories,
for which a single can of soda
could send you over the limit,
an added sugar limit exceeded
by 90% of Americans.
In 2017 the American Heart Association
released their guidelines
for children, recommending they get no
more than about 6 teaspoons per day,
which means there’s nearly a
hundred cereals on the U.S. market
for which a single serving exceeded
the entire recommended daily limit.
And the heart association recommends
no added sugars at all under age 2,
small toddlers are to avoid
added sugars altogether,
a recommendation that’s violated…
in up to 80% of toddlers.
The U.S. is one of at least 65
countries that have implemented
dietary guidelines or policies
to curb sugar consumption.
In the UK, the Scientific
Advisory Committee on Nutrition
made new recommendations to
reduce added sugars down to 5%,
which is the direction the World
Health Organization is headed as well.
They always seem to be
ahead of the curve.  Why?
Because their policy-making
process is at least partially
protected from industry influence.
Unlike governments, which may have
competing interests in commerce
and trade, the World Health Organization
is exclusively concerned with health.